CURRICULUM VITAE

Adrian C. Gallo

Crops and Soil Sciences Dept. 380 Peavy Forest Science Center Oregon State University Corvallis, OR 97330

mobile: (925) 354 - 6772 adrian.gallo@oregonstate.edu

office: (541) 737 - 3180

RESEARCH INTERESTS

My ongoing academic research focuses on the mechanisms behind soil carbon sequestration and nutrient cycling processes across different ecosystems in North America. My research also involves forest carbon cycling in a long-term soil productivity research network. Recently, I have begun to appreciate the socio-political-economic constraints of land management decisions and hope to contribute to a better-informed soil carbon policy framework.

management (decisions and hope to contribute to a better-informed son carbon poncy framework.
EDUCATION	ı
2022	Expected Ph.D. in Soil Science, Oregon State University, OR.
2016	M.S. Sustainable Forest Management, Oregon State University, OR
2013	B.S. Soil Science, Geology Minor, California Polytechnic State University, CA
RESEARCH	PROJECTS
2018-2019	Learning Innovation Grant through Oregon State University for 3D
	Landslide Model. Co-Author with Erin Rooney. \$12,000
2017-2019	Effects on soil and aquatic organic matter in a southern Appalachian
	hardwood forest: A rapid assessment across the terrestrial-aquatic
	interface following the Great Smokey Mountains National Park fire of
	2016. NSF – Macrosystems Biology.
2016-Present	A Continental scale assessment of the linkages between soil organic
	matter stabilization mechanisms, controls, and vulnerability. NSF –
2012 2016	Macrosystems Biology.
2013-2016	Northwest Advanced Renewables Alliance (NARA): A new vista for
	green fuels, chemicals, and Environmentally Preferred Products (EPPs) USDA-AFRI.
	USDA-AFKI.
POSITIONS 1	HELD
2021 Fall	Instructor of Record. SOIL 205 & SOIL 206 - Intro to Soil Science
	Lecture & Intro to Soil Science Laboratory. Oregon State University.

POSITIONS HELD	
2021 Fall	Instructor of Record. SOIL 205 & SOIL 206 - Intro to Soil Science
	Lecture & Intro to Soil Science Laboratory. Oregon State University.
	Cascades Campus, Bend, OR.
2021 Summer	Student Hourly Worker . E-campus SOIL 205 – Oregon State University
2021 Spring	Instructor of Record . Forestry 206 - Forest Soils Lab for Intro to Soils
	Science & Forestry 208 – Forest Soils [Online offering]. Oregon State
	University
2020 Fall	Graduate Teaching Assistant. Soil 205 Intro to Environmental Science
	Lab. Oregon State University
2020 Summer	Extension Communications Student Intern. Oregon State University
2019-20 Winter	Freelance Consultant, Indigo Ag Inc. Charlestown, Massachusetts

2019 Fall	Graduate Teacher's Assistant. Forest Engineering 430/530 Watershed
	Processes
2019 Spring	Instructor of Record . Forestry 206 - Forest Soils Lab for Intro to Soils
	Science & Forestry 208 – Forest Soils [Online version]
2018 Spring	Graduate Teachers Assistant . Forestry 206 - Forest Soils Lab for Intro to
	Soils Science & Forestry 208 – Forest Soils [Online version]
2016-Present	Graduate Research Assistant. Dept. Crop and Soil Sciences, Oregon
	State University, OR
2013-2016	Graduate Research Assistant. Dept. Forest Engineering, Resources, and
	Management, Oregon State University, OR
2013 Fall & Winter	Student instructor . <i>Intro to Soil Science Lab – SOIL 121</i> . Natural
	Resource Management & Environmental Sciences (NRES) Dept.
	California Polytechnic State University, CA.
2012-2013	Laboratory Manager. Natural Resource Management & Environmental
	Sciences (NRES) Dept. California Polytechnic State University, CA.
2012 Summer	Watershed Restoration Scientist. USDA Forest Service & Geological
	Society of America. Cave Junction, OR.
2011 Summer	Biological Science Technician of Natural Resources (Soils GS-5).
	USDA Forest Service. Craig, AK. Award
2010 Summer	Biological Science Technician of Natural Resources (Soils GS-4).
	USDA Forest Service. Craig, AK.

PROFES.	SIONAL	SERVICES
	JIONAL	DEIX VICEO

THOTESOTOTITE	2211,1023
2015-2017	Executive Board Member for Oregon Society of Soil Scientists (OSSS) at
	Oregon State University
2015-2016	Executive Board Member for Association of Graduate Soil Scientists
	(AGSS) at Oregon State University.
2014-2016	Planning Committee for Western Forestry Graduate Research Symposium
	(WFGRS) at Oregon State University.
2013-Present	House Director for Phi Kappa Psi Fraternity at Oregon State University.

AWARDS

111111111111111111111111111111111111111	
2019	Best Overall Student Presentation. Soil Chemistry Division. SSSA. San Antonio, TX.
2017	,
2015	Best Overall Presentation. WFGRS. Corvallis, OR.
2014	Best Poster in Session – Wildand Soils Division. SSSA. Long Beach, CA.
2014	Rick Stratchan Graduate Research Fellowship. FERM Dept. Corvallis,
	OR.
2012	Professional Soil Scientist of the Year. NRES Dept. San Luis Obispo, CA
2011	Certificate of Outstanding Job Performance. USDA Forest Service. Craig,
	AK.
2011	Royce Lambert Undergraduate Scholarship. NRES Dept. San Luis
	Obispo, CA.

Antioch, CA.

OUTREACH & EXTRACURRICULAR ACTIVITIES

2018-2021	Soil Matter Blog: Porous Pavement & Trail Erosion & Mountain Biking
2016	Soil Science Information Booth with OSSS at Oregon State Fair. Salem,

OR.

2015-Present FM Radio & Podcast Producer on Science Communication in Graduate

School. <u>Inspiration Dissemination</u>. Oregon State University 88.7 KBVR

FM. See author list & podcast.

MEMBERSHIP IN ACADEMIC SOCIETIES

2015-Present	American Geophysical Union (AGU)	
2015-Present	Northwest Forest Soils Council (NWFSC)	
2013-Present	Oregon Society of Soil Scientists (OSSS)	
2012-Present	Geological Society of America (GSA)	
2011-2013	California Forest Soil Council (CFSC)	
2009-2019	Crops Science Society of America (CSSA)	
2009-2019	Agronomy Society of America (ASA)	
2009-Present	Soil Science Society of America (SSSA)	

PUBLICATIONS

In Prep	A.C. Gallo, J.A. Hatten, S. Holub, K. Lajtha, K. Littke, D. Maguire.
	Effects on soil temperature, moisture and soil respiration two years
	following intensive organic matter and compaction manipulations in the
	Oregon Cascades.
In Prep	A.C. Gallo, J.A. Hatten, S. Holub, K. Lajtha, K. Littke. Root carbon
	contributions are uniform across intensive biomass removal treatments
	resulting in soil carbon storage resiliency.
2021	A.R. Possinger, A.R., T.L. Weiglein, M. Bowman, A. Gallo, J.A. Hatten,
	K.A. Heckman, L. Matosziuk, L.E. Nave, M. SanClements, C.W.
	Swanston, B.D. Strahm. Climate effects on subsoil carbon loss mediated
	by soil chemistry. Environmental Science and Technology.
	https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.est.1c04909
2021	Weiglein, T.L, M. Bowman, A.C. Gallo, J.A. Hatten, K.A. Heckman, L.
	Matosziuk, L.E. Nave, A.R. Possinger, M. SanClements,
	C.W. Swanston, B.D. Strahm. Key predictors of soil organic matter
	vulnerability to mineralization differ with depth at a continental scale.
	Biogeochemistry. https://doi.org/10.1007/s10533-021-00856-x
2021	L.E. Nave, M. Bowman, A. Gallo, J.A. Hatten, K.A. Heckman, L.
	Matosziuk, A.R. Possinger, M. SanClements, J. Sanderman, B.D. Strahm,
	T.L. Weiglein, C.W. Swanston. 2021. Patterns and predictors of soil

	organic carbon storage across a continental-scale network.
	Biogeochemistry. https://doi.org/10.1007/s10533-020-00745-9
2020 Invited Review	Carter, T.L, L.L. Jennings, Y. Pressler, A.C. Gallo, A.A. Berhe, E. Marin-
	Spiotta, C. Shepard, T. Ghezzehei, K.L. Vaughan. 2020. Towards diverse
	representation and inclusion in soil science in the United States. Soil
	Science Society of America Journal. https://doi.org/10.1002/saj2.20210
2020	Heckman, K.A., L.E. Nave, M. Bowman, A. Gallo, J.A. Hatten, L.M.
	Matosziuk, A.R. Possinger, M. SanClements, B.D. Strahm, T.L. Weiglein,
	C. Rasmussen, C.W. Swanston. 2020. Divergent controls on carbon
	concentration and persistence between forests and grasslands of the
	conterminous US. Biogeochemistry. https://doi.org/10.1007/s10533-020-
	<u>00725-z</u>
2020	Littke, K., T. Harrington, R. Slesak, S. Holub, J. Hatten, A. Gallo, W.
	Littke, R. Harrison, E. Turnblom. 2020. Impacts of organic matter removal
	and vegetation control on nutrition and growth of Douglas-fir at three
	Pacific Northwestern Long-Term Soil Productivity sites. Forest Ecology
	and Management. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foreco.2020.118176
2020	Matosziuk, L., A. Gallo, J. Hatten, K.D. Bladon, D. Ruud, M. Bowman, J.
	Egan, K. Heckman, M. SanClements, B. Strahm, T. Weiglein. 2020.
	Short-term effects of recent fire on the production and translocation of
	pyrogenic carbon in Great Smoky Mountains National Park. Frontiers in
	Forest and Global Change. https://doi.org/10.3389/ffgc.2020.00006
2020	M. SanClements, R.H. Lee, E. Ayres, K. Goodman, M. Jones, F. Furfen,
	K. Thibault, R. Zulueta, J. Roberti, C. Lunch, A. Gallo. Collaborating with
	NEON. BioScience. https://doi.org/10.1093/biosci/biaa005
2019	Nave, L.E., A. Covarrubias Ornelas, P.E. Drevnick, A. Gallo, J.A.
	Hatten, K.A. Heckman, L. Matosziuk, M. Sanclements, B.D. Strahm, T.J.
	Veverica, T.L. Weiglein, C.W. Swanston. 2019. Carbon-mercury
	interactions in Spodosols assessed through density fractionation,
	radiocarbon analysis, and soil survey information. Soil Science Society of
	America Journal. https://doi.org/10.2136/sssaj2018.06.0227

CONFERENCE PRESENTATIONS (First Author)

COTT ENERTICE THE	ESETTITIONS (THE TRUMOT)
2019	Roots to Regolith: Sources of organic matter across the National
	Ecological Observatory Network (NEON) soil plots. Oral Presentation.
	SSSA. San Antonio, TX.
2019	Sources of organic matter: A latitudinal assessment of carbon
	contributions down soil profiles. Oral Presentation. San Diego.
2019	The morphology of burnt dirt: A pedologic investigation of fire history
	across ecosystems. Poster Presentation. SSSA. San Diego. Best Poster in
	Student Session.
2018	Root carbon contributions are uniform across intensive biomass removal
	treatments in a western Oregon Douglas-fir forest. North American Forest
	Soils Council Meeting. Poster Presentation. Quebec City, Quebec.

2017	Root carbon contributions are uniform across intensive biomass removal treatments in a Western Oregon Douglas-fir forest. SSSA. Oral Presentation. Tampa, FL.
2016	Does root carbon from harvest trees replace mineral carbon? Oral Presentation. AGU. San Francisco, CA.
2016	Does Root Carbon from Harvested Trees Replace Mineral Carbon? Effects of LTSP Treatments in a Western Oregon Douglas-fir Forest. Presentation. SSSA. Phoenix, AZ.
2015	Soil Organic Matter Dynamics in an Intensively Managed Douglas-fir Forest. Poster Presentation. SSSA. Minneapolis, MN.
2015	Soil Organic Matter Dynamics in an Intensively Managed Douglas-fir Forest. Poster Presentation. Annual NARA Conference. Spokane, WA
2015	Biophysical responses in soil following intensive biomass and compaction treatments. Oral Presentation. WFGRS. Corvallis, OR. <i>Best Overall Presentation</i> .
2015	Immediate response mechanisms to account for sustained tree growth following intensive biomass removal on LTSP sites. Northwest Forest Soils Council. Oral Presentation. Hood River, Oregon.
2014	Immediate response mechanisms to account for sustained tree growth following intensive biomass removal on long-term soil productivity (LTSP) sites. Poster Presentation. SSSA. Long Beach, CA. Best Poster in Session.
2014	Immediate response mechanisms to account for sustained tree growth following intensive biomass removal on long-term soil productivity (LTSP) sites. Poster Presentation. WFGRS. Corvallis, OR.
2014	Biophysical response in soil following intensive biomass and compaction treatments. Poster Presentation. Northwest Advanced Renewables Alliance (NARA) Annual Meeting. Seattle, WA.

GELECT CONFEDENCE DEGENTATIONS (C. A. (L. 1)		
	FERENCE PRESENTATIONS (Co-Authored)	
2019	Impact of freeze-thaw cycles on porosity in permafrost affected soils. Erin	
	Rooney. SSSA. Oral Presentation. San Antonio, TX.	
2019	Predictors of soil organic matter vulnerability to decomposition in mineral	
	horizons from a continental-scale sample set. Tyler Weiglein. Oral	
	Presentation. SSSA. San Antonio, TX.	
2019	Linking nominal oxidation state of carbon from extracted soil organic	
	matter to cumulative respiration from climate change incubations at a	
	continental scale. Maggie Bowman. Oral Presentation. SSSA. San	
	Antonio, TX.	
2019	Linking carbon and nitrogen speciation with soil organic matter	
	persistence at the continental scale. Angela Possinger. Oral Presentation.	
	SSSA. San Antonio, TX.	
2019	Fire effects on soil organic matter in a southern Appalachian hardwood	
	forest: movement of fire-altered organic matter in soil and aquatic	
	systems, Jeff Hatten, Oral Presentation, SSSA, San Diego, CA.	

2017	Assessing soil organic C stability at the continental scale: An analysis of soil C and radiocarbon profiles across the NEON sites. Katherine
	Heckman. Oral Presentation. AGU. New Orleans, LA.
2017	Forest and rangeland soil and the carbon cycle. USFS National Soils
	Assessment. Jeff Hatten. Boise, ID.
2016	An assessment of soil organic matter stabilization mechanisms on a
	continental scale. Macrosystem Biology PI Meeting. Katherine Heckman.
	Poster Presentation. Washington, D.C.
2011	Heavy metals as indicators of Serpentenitic soils. Oral Presentation.
	SSSA. Laurie Fraser. San Antonio, TX.